In this episode of In the Know, you'll
hear our reaction to Bill Aman's very
interesting tweet. You'll also find out
why we're not worried about inflation
and what the credit markets are thinking
about this AI revolution.
Well, greetings everyone. It is
employment Friday once again and here we
are in the know. Uh so as usual we'll go
through fiscal policy, monetary policy,
market indicator, economic indicators
and market indicators. Uh but I'm going
to start uh a little differently this
time. We're going to feature first a
tweet by Bill Aman and then a number of
slides to explain uh in more detail uh
the letter that I wrote within the last
10 days. really putting into context our
outlook for much stronger than expected
real GDP growth, much lower than
expected inflation, but interest rates
moving up influenced much more by real
growth than by inflation. Uh in other
words, the market is working and uh and
uh profitability at probably all-time
highs. We're we're almost there now. uh
but we think we will hit all-time highs
thanks to the productivity gains we
expect out of AI and all of the
technologies around which we have
centered our research. So let's start
with uh the tweet from Bill Aman. I
thought it was very interesting and one
of the reasons is um when I first
started in this business now I was in
college and it was the late 70s uh but
this argument the one that Bill is
putting forth uh was prevalent back then
uh and but it was more predicated on
just inflation stuck in the double
digits and uh and the this idea that
interest costs would continue to rise
feeding the inflation rate. So a vicious
cycle. Uh we actually think that uh that
this time is going to play out very
similarly
uh to the 80s. And in the 80s what we
saw was real growth picking up thanks to
productivity, inflation coming down. uh
and in one of the reasons inflation was
coming down is we were in a little bit
of a technology revolution uh really
started by the PC and then software. Uh
that did feed some of the
disinflationary
effects we saw back then. uh today we
think the five major innovation P
platforms so AI, robotics, energy
storage, blockchain technology and
multiomic sequencing. Those five major
technologically enabled innovation
platforms are going to uh are going to
drive inflation down to much lower
levels uh than most people uh expect.
And in fact, we would not be surprised
to see deflation, especially if oil
prices crack the way we expect them to.
Uh so with that, I'll go into the charts
now that uh I featured in my letter uh
and explain them perhaps a little bit
more. So here's the first one. Now, talk
about long term. We're going back to
1790.
Uh and really piecing the the interest
rate picture together uh prior to the
1900s uh is quite the task. Uh uh and we
worked uh with academic research. Nick
Gruce actually did a lot of this work
for us in 2019 when we first published a
piece uh about uh long-term interest
rates and inverted yield curves. Uh but
what I'd like to point out from this
chart is we've seen a big spike in
interest rates and boy does it feel like
a big spike. uh we got down below one I
think during COVID and now we're above
five on the 10-year Treasury yield. Uh
but look at it in the context of history
and you'll see that where the the rate
is today is really at the midpoint of
and and maybe the midpoint of where we
were uh on average going back to 1790.
although certainly higher than we were
for for um large parts of history here.
Um, and the other thing I wanted to
point out was really the anomaly in
terms of history is not what's going on
now. Uh, but what happened in the 70s,
80s, and 90s, uh, and and really up to
COVID, uh, the big spike in rates. And
we link that, uh, to a couple of things.
Most important, we went off the gold
exchange standard in 1971. We closed the
gold window. And what had been happening
before that was starting with uh the
Vietnam War and then the Great Society
program. So it's called guns and butter.
Government was financing everything and
spending
uh you know spending was somewhat out of
control then. uh that was all
accommodated by monetary policy and that
and and which became unhinged around the
gold uh closing of the gold window and
all hell broke loose and from a monetary
point of view we ended up at
double-digit inflation and it took us a
long time to work out of that. Uh we
think we went too far in the other
direction. The market stopped working.
the Fed was really feeding the economy,
spoon feeding. Uh there was still a lot
of fear after 08 09 and uh uh and then
again in COVID, but now we think we're
back into a situation where the market
is working and this Fed I think is going
to be very good uh for for for all of
us. Uh so now this is PCE inflation. Um,
we're focused on this because Fed
Chairman Worsh is focused on headline
PCE inflation. So, we got an update. Uh,
when we first produced this chart, it
was 3.7% with the update and there was a
little bit of a downward revision. Uh,
we are down to 3.4% on a year-over-year
basis. Um, you can see core is a little
bit lower than that. The problem is uh I
think Fed Chairman Worsh is fixated on
headline or at least he says he is uh
and it is a long way from 2%. Uh and so
we heard a lot of hawkish top talk
meaning the Fed is going to keep
tightening. The Fed is going to to keep
tightening until this uh this report
came out on PCE inflation still very
high. But if we go through and look at a
private measure of inflation, which we
believe Fed Chairman Worsh is focused on
private metrics as well. Uh here you can
see uh trueflation. We featured this
before. Uh you can see that uh if you
look at the headline we it has picked up
that's in the purple there to roughly
2.7 with oil prices probably a big part
of the recent tick up but look at what's
happening to core. Core is continuing to
tick down. Uh and we don't think this is
lost on Fed Chairman Walsh. And you can
see that uh if you look at pre uh
precoid, we're really moving into the
averages we saw back then. Uh and here
you can see the dollar. This is uh
another again long-term chart, not as
long as the last one. Uh but we we like
to point out the early 80s here that you
see in green with the dollar. Uh back
then uh we had excellent uh monetary
policy and fiscal policy that was very
businessfriendly.
Lots of tax cuts uh and uh deregulation
as well similar to the environment we're
in today. And uh and some may uh argue
with that uh but we do think we're in a
businessfriendly uh climate here. And we
see that the AI revolution by and large
has started from the United States. Uh
in fact uh one of the statistics I saw
in Bloomberg this month is that if you
look at all the data center financing in
the world uh 90% of it and this is uh
based on fixed income metrics 90% of it
is in the United States. Uh so I I do
think what has happened with our uh
corporate tax rates the effective tax
tax rates now being uh the lowest in the
world we think around 8% because of the
accelerated uh depreciation
uh for new manufacturing facilities and
certainly data centers uh qualify for
that 100% depreciation
uh in the first year of service. Uh that
means that these companies are seeing
massive tax refunds that they can
redeploy into more investment in the
United States. And we're seeing an
investment boom. Uh what that meant in
the early 80s was that uh the return on
invested capital and this is true today
in the US was moving up relative to that
in the rest of the world. And what
happened was the dollar went up. You can
see how dramatically it went up back
then. Um well, we're uh coming from a
bit of a different level. In the late
70s, the dollar was shellacked by
horrible fiscal and monetary policy. Uh
and so it was coming from uh a quite a
low level and uh and very low
expectations. This time around you can
see the dollar uh on this basis. This is
the DXY against just six countries. Uh
it's closer to the higher end of recent
ranges. Uh but we think it is going to
continue to move up for the same reason
it did in in uh the early 80s. Uh a lot
of the narratives out there would
suggest that uh the dollar is done and
American exceptionalism is done. Uh we
disagree with that. I think uh what the
statistic I mentioned about uh data
centers uh would speak to that. Uh and
we do think the pressure is going to be
up again because of foreign direct
investment and other kinds of investment
moving more towards the US uh because of
businessfriendly policies. Now here's
Kelshi uh as you know we're we are
partnering with Kelshi. I think I think
anyone can partner with Kali and
contribute uh ideas to make new markets
uh new prediction markets. Um and you'll
see here what was very interesting as we
uh started this um this market is the
the that Khi got this more right uh than
I think many people expected. When we
started this, the actual level of the
dollar was I think around 98 on the DXY.
Uh now it's a little above 100. Uh
Kelshi had uh the expectations
always above 100 and in fact when they
started out you can see here 103 10500.
So, so there was something uh in uh the
the mind of people who were uh who were
placing bets on this market uh that uh
the dollar was going to be stronger than
when we started and as it turns out that
is true. It did go down and now it's
turning around. So we found that kind of
fascinating and we will be uh doing more
with Kelshi uh in this in terms of
economic statistics and other statistics
uh in the months ahead. Um here is
something fascinating. Uh this is the
dollar again. Now the DXY which we just
uh showed you uh that is uh how most
people think about the dollar the
financial markets you know people making
judgment calls about the dollar
investment decisions about the dollar uh
they're fixated on DXY
um but this is the real trade weighted
dollar it's uh produced by the Fed and
it involves 26 different countries and
you can see relative to history that the
dollar looks like it's not that far from
its all-time highs. You can also see the
early 80s here. Um what happened to the
dollar on this basis uh but how much
higher we are now than even we were back
then on the DXY just to revert back to
that quickly. You can see that, you
know, if if you believed this chart, uh
that the dollar is much weaker than it
was back then. According to the Fed's
measure, uh that is not true. And the
dollar going up, and as I said, we think
it will return to all-time highs on this
basis. Um the dollar going up is a
powerful anti-inflationary force,
especially because most commodities are
priced in dollars. Uh here's the gold
price. So, you can say the dollar is up
near all-time highs and and that's good
uh because commodities are priced in
dollars. But if you're looking at gold,
uh our monetary policy in the last I
would say it looks like 15 20 years has
been very bad. Uh the dollar has lost a
lot of purchasing power relative to
gold. Now uh you see in green there we
highlight what the dollar did during
Vulkar's term and Greenspan's term and
we have a suspicion even though they did
not say so explicitly that they were
managing monetary policy using uh the
gold price as one of their prime
indicators.
uh and uh when it went down uh it they
gave them more room to ease. When it
went up uh they were more in a
tightening mode. Uh as you can see um
the the gold price started going up uh
went up to its prior high um under
Greenspan and then he left office and
you can see since then very bad track
record. Interestingly, uh the do the
gold price peaked the day or the day
after that uh that President Trump
appointed uh Kevin Walsh to be Fed
chairman. uh and it has been down since
then. And we would not be surprised to
see it continue to decline uh as as he
gets uh this um this monetary policy
under some kind of disciplined control
um using price indicators.
Uh here you can see the the oil price
and we think that the oil price has
levitated over these last 20 25 years.
Um partly because of monetary
accommodation which is the same reason
the gold price went up. Um but if we're
right uh the combination of uh
disciplined monetary po policy using
more of a price rule like the gold price
maybe not the gold price but like the
gold price uh and the fact that uh
innovation technologically enabled
innovation is is going to really put a
big dent in the global demand for oil
57% % of oil uh consumption is for
transportation and we believe
transportation is moving away from uh
gasoline powered cars and engines
elsewhere and diesel-powered
uh trucks to electric. Uh and so we we
do believe that uh that the oil demand
has been in the process of peaking ever
since this uh transition started and it
it started in earnest in China uh and
Europe. Uh US is uh following. Um but uh
we do believe that the oil price could
drop into the 30 to $35 range. Uh and
the reason we say that is you can see
during the various crisis crises it's
dropped to that range. In fact during
COVID it dropped well below that range.
Um and so now uh this won't be a crisis.
It'll be a technological shift that's
taking it back down and that certainly
will help inflation expectations.
Um here's another thing that is going to
impact inflation mightily. Uh you can
see the two learning curves here. The
one in blue is for genomic sequencing.
Uh and just to give you what we've
pictured here, it's a it's a it's
Wright's law in action. And it says for
every cumulative doubling in the number
of whole human genome sequence, cost
decline by 40%. That's the learning
curve for uh uh genomic sequencing. Uh
for AI inference, the learning curve
that's in black uh is much more
dramatic. It gives you a sense of how
much more quickly innovation is
happening today for
oh and on this basis we're not even
using rights law. I'll give you an
annual uh number. um the cost of AI
inference. So what it costs for chat GBT
to answer your questions um and this is
at a fixed performance level. uh the
costs dropping 99.99%
per year [snorts]
uh and uh and and so any any activity
that involves AI is going to experience
significant cost declines. Now, Jevan's
paradox would uh have um have us believe
and we do believe that as the prices for
AI come down, for AI inference come
down, the volume will explode and the
revenue growth, think open AI,
Anthropic,
uh think uh SpaceX AI uh and Muse now um
those th the volume growth associated
with those kinds of price declines uh is
going to be explosive and that's why uh
we've seen uh o uh open AAI's uh revenue
go from 20 billion that's the annualized
revenue run rate at the end of last year
to uh 70 billion they just reported uh
which uh surpasses the 65 billion
reported for July lie for Anthropic. So
I'm sure Anthropic is higher than 65
billion. So they are back neck and neck
again probably. Um but despite those
price declines and uh that the revenue
growth is is exploding, we've never seen
anything like this. And that's kind of a
microcosm uh that we expect for the
economy as a whole. Um we expect that as
these price declines seep into the
economy more and more deeply and they
will uh that uh the volume growth
associated with any given activity is
going to accelerate uh fairly
significantly and that is how we get to
uh an outside outsized uh um GDP growth
forecast in the years ahead. Um so and
and here's uh in action so to speak how
we look at the world. Um we look at the
world as you know through a technology
lens. Uh and here you can see the 15
technologies involved in those five
major innovation platforms. And you can
see how they are converging. And you can
see how AI in purple is uh is having the
biggest impact on the other
technologies. So the cost declines
impacting AI will be feeding into these
other technologies. And I often say when
we first, and I should give Brett
Winton, our chief futurist, the the
credit for for drawing this, when we
first drew this chart, I think there
were I don't know if there were any
lines between uh the the gold section
there, blockchain technology and AI. But
now there are because of Agentic
Payments, Agentic Commerce, uh Grockbot,
Muse, uh and uh and now bots from uh
Open AI. Uh so we're going to uh we
believe see a lot of deflationary
pressure, but is good deflation uh
meaning it causes a boom in growth. Uh,
and I'll just round out the the the red
there is robotics, the green is uh
energy storage, and the blue is
multiomic sequencing. And as you can
see, AI is going to have a profound
impact on them all and is probably going
to speed up uh the innovation in all of
these areas relative to what it would
have been without AI.
Now here
is uh global re uh real GDP growth. Uh
again thanks to Brett Winton uh in uh in
consultation with academic research and
academic researchers. Uh he's come up
with this uh with this growth chart or
growth timeline going way back to a
100,000 BC. And he's going to go into
more detail in this year's big ideas. Um
uh and uh you'll see that as we carry
out this um this chart to 2036 the
growth rates go higher but you can see
uh what happened uh from 1500 to600 is
you know pretty much we stayed at a 0.6%
uh real GDP growth rate as best as
academic research can help us
understand. Uh actually I think he might
be refining that down to 0.5 and I think
that's really good because I think there
was a little bit of false precision with
that 0.6.
uh but you can see what we expect from
real GDP growth uh for or what we did
expect for the five years ended in 2030
um 7.3%
so 7 to 8% and we've been going around
with this forecast and of course most
people think that's crazy um because
we've never lived through a regime
change like this we didn't go through
the industrial revolution and so we've
just been living in this 3% GDP world.
Uh well, this is a technology revolution
and we think it's bigger than the
industrial revolution. So, you can see
going from 0.6 to three, that was a
five-fold increase in the growth rate.
Uh we actually do believe we're going to
overtime see much more than a five-fold
uh increase in the growth rate. It may
take a while to get there or maybe it
won't. We don't know. This is all
happening uh so much more quickly than
we expected. But we do believe that uh
we'll see, you know, high singledigit
real GDP growth. But the other side of
that is that we will see much lower than
expected inflation, perhaps deflation,
uh if these technologies converge the
way we think they will. And you can see
there the IMF forecast at 3%. Actually I
think the IMF forecast has gone down to
two and a half percent or something like
that. Uh so effectively the IMF is is
saying these technologies are not going
to have any impact on real GDP growth.
Um we disagree and uh that's what makes
markets. Uh so uh stay tuned for our big
ideas. It'll be out in January. uh and
this chart will be updated. Now why does
that growth rate accelerate? It
accelerates because of productivity and
you can see in the 80s and 90s uh from a
trend sense we had an upward shift in uh
in productivity as the PC and software
came into being and then the wireless
and smartphones and so forth. uh we
think we'll see a replay so that uh
productivity growth uh accelerates into
the five to six% plus range. Uh that
would make sense given uh where we think
technology is going. Now this was an
interesting again long-term chart. Uh
give credit to Nick Gruce who's now
director of research for uh consumer AI
and fintech. Um, but here is the yield
curve. So, the 10-year Treasury yield uh
versus the two-year Treasury yield. Um,
and you can see that back in the
industrial revolution, uh, we had an
inverted yield curve more often than we
had a positively sloped yield curve.
What that meant was long rates below
short rates. Uh and then we had uh the
depression. Um we had the Fed. The Fed
was put into existence in 1913.
And since then whenever any investor has
seen an inverted yield curve um he or
she has basically assumed correctly that
we were heading into a recession. That
was not true. Now you can see there were
a lot more recessions uh back then
before the Fed uh and that's because we
were on the gold standard a price rule
and so the adjustment uh the adjustment
had to be taken in volume or unit growth
uh in order to keep the price rule in
effect. uh and so but you can see that
we had inverted yield curves before
recessions after recessions uh again
more than 60% of the time. Um,
interestingly, the last uh inverted
yield curve we had and it was quite a
lengthy one in the context of uh
postworld war II history uh was uh after
COVID when the Fed raised interest rates
22 or 24fold within 16 months. We went
into an inverted yield curve and we
think we were in a rolling recession. Uh
certainly that's what housing,
manufacturing, small business, uh lower
income consumers, they were all in
recession, but the economy never fell
into a recession, which is very
interesting. And um maybe taking us back
to uh the industrial revolution when the
yield curve was inverted more than 60%
of the time on average by 100 basis
points. So we shall see.
Um and then yes uh just to get a little
bit at that uh many of you who have been
paying attention or tuning into uh in
the know that I have been very intrigued
by this chart. I know it's kind of geeky
but I am a geek when it comes to
economic statistics and the yield curve
in particular. I was struck that during
COVID or we did not as the Fed and and
the government generally, governments
around the world both from a fiscal and
monetary point of view uh did uh they
they put the accelerator to the floor,
everyone at the same time. And yet we
could not get back to that 200 to 300
basis point of steepness in the yield
curve. And I was thinking, okay, what
does that mean? Uh I think what it means
and I I and this last turn down from we
didn't even get to 150 basis points like
we did during COVID as the yield curve
was steepening. Um we got to roughly 75
and now we're down into the 40s. Uh what
does this mean? I do think it means that
uh Treasury yields are stiffing sniffing
out some deflationary
undercurrens out there. In other words,
that the inflation expectations
inside the long-term Treasury, and we'll
go into that in a second, but those
inflation expectations
are pretty tame and maybe getting tamer.
Um, now that's not what's quite shown
with uh inflation as implied by tips,
but uh yet, but we think that's where
this is going. Um,
so uh let's let's do just a quick run
through some of the charts. I know I've
uh used a lot of time with the letter or
a summary of the letter. Uh but we'll go
through a few charts here. I'll skip
through some, but here's the deficit.
Uh, we're at mid5%.
Uh, Bessant expects 3% by the end of
this term, this the the presidential
term. Uh, we think uh he's right and
that's because we think nominal GDP
growth will be a lot lower than people
expect. And this is uh how we started
turning things around in the 80s as well
under Reagan and then when we got into
the 90s um even more so with Clinton. So
um uh stay tuned. Uh this is um this is
what people fear. So they're worried. We
we see in the headlines we're at $40
trillion dollar of government debt now.
This is terrible. It's above our GDP.
Um and what we say is we we agree we
think there's too much government
spending because uh government spending
is taxation period either now or in the
future or through inflation. So we agree
with that. Uh but we don't think the
consequences right now are as dire as
many would think. Uh why is that? Well
uh if you look at debt to GDP, you're
comparing a balance sheet statistic with
an income statement statistic.
So what people would say a stock versus
a flow. Um and uh and and so that's one
way to look at it. Uh but there's
another way to look at it uh more like
for like debt to equity both of those
are balance sheet items and you can see
on that basis
uh we're near nearer to the low uh in
the context of this history uh than we
are to a high. In other words, the
wealth generation in this economy and
the growth uh are are um are taking the
edge off of this statistic. Again, I
agree with the sentiment that government
spending is too high. And of course, the
recent government spending is um in
large part about defense spending. So,
national security, I am for that. uh but
uh I do think government uh spending
generally needs to be brought under more
control. Um here is uh another again
long-term chart. Um, you know, I think
the reason the bond market and equity,
everybody's a little confused, uh, is
because we went through 40 years when
nominal GDP growth decelerated
mostly because of inflation and interest
rates followed. And now we're on the
other side of this. Um, well, I think
this is good news. I know it's not good
news for bond holders who don't like
seeing um you know their their principal
whacked. Uh but uh I I do think it's
more uh a testimony of what is going on
in terms of accelerating growth and I
think uh these few charts will show you.
This is the five-year Treasury yield and
you can see the real yield. So broken
down between inflation and real, you can
see the recent interest rate move is
much more a function of real yields than
it is a function of inflation.
Uh so you can see I find it very
interesting. I know fixed income
investors uh pay attention to every
basis point and uh of course we in the
uh in in the equity market probably are
just more focused on percentage points
so 100 basis points uh but you'd think
some days that that as as fixed income
investors and reporters are talking
about uh inflation implied
uh in the bond market that inflation was
moving out of control. Uh we look at
this and say, okay, looks like the bond
market market expects this five-year
inflation rate uh to behave pretty well.
Uh sure, it's above 2%. Um but it's kind
of been steady state for the last uh for
the last few years. Uh we actually think
it will break down uh once these um once
the impact of technology uh is
understood more and more by the markets
its impact on on inflation.
Um I'm just going to rip through some of
these charts quickly. This is a
four-year annualiz four-year uh
annualized growth rate in federal
outlays and money. And you can see
federal outlays are up uh with defense
spending a big part of uh the increase
recently. Um but monetary policy is not
accommodating it. Uh so the last few
years of monetary policy the growth rate
of of the M in the low single digits not
accommodating this. Um and uh so so so
that's that's good news. That means it's
not going to be inflationary. And you
can see uh you can see what happened in
the uh 80s 90s uh that the the money
growth rate was much higher and velocity
increased which was a big problem. Uh
and here's velocity uh speaking of it um
the closest correlation we see velocity
has been falling. Another reason um
another reason the uh money growth rates
uh did not cause inflation is because
velocity the rate at which money turns
over was falling. The only the only
statistic that we see that peaked in the
late 90s uh like velocity is the labor
participation rate. Uh and you can see
it's been falling recently. It did tick
up in today's report. Uh that was good.
Uh some of it may be because uh
affordability
and you know more people coming back
into the labor force just to make ends
meet. Um if that continues maybe
velocity turns around. We don't think it
will continue uh because baby boomers
are retiring and immigrants have been
leaving. So uh the velocity of money
should not uh we think it will flatten
out here. It seems to be flattening out
uh and will not be turbocharging money
growth. Um here you can see money growth
at 5 point I believe that's 5.7
uh and many people worried that the
inflation rate will follow. Um,
understandably, uh, if if velocity
weren't flattening out and and rolling
over, we'd, uh, we'd probably be
wondering this ourselves. Um, here you
can see very importantly, diffusion
index. This is what, uh, Fed Chairman
Worsh is watching and you can see the
diffusion index. Um and this is uh the
categories of inflation that are 0.3 or
higher. And he didn't like the direction
of those. Well, you can see we're seeing
now a quick reversal. The the blue there
or purple is the six-month diffusion
rate. And we think that is going to
build momentum on the downside and pull
the annual one down as well.
Uh so very important uh uh piece of
information. Employment uh today just to
run through that quickly much lower than
expected employment if you use non-farm
payroll. If you use household employment
which is this one it was 400 and
something thousand. So again something
for everyone. The more important point
is on a year-over-year basis this has
been pretty flat. It's been pretty
volatile month-to-month, but pretty
flat. Uh, so that's employment, but
labor, the labor force growth has also
dropped off. Uh, as I mentioned earlier,
partly boomers, partly uh, immigrants
leaving. Um, so, uh, we've got an
unemployment rate in the green there,
uh, that has been quite well behaved in
this rolling recession that we've been
in. Uh, and so it's at 4.2. two, but do
look at the the the purple line that
that's the 16 to 24 year old age cohort.
That is back at 9.9%. So those uh you
know uh students leaving college uh
having trouble finding jobs. uh go out,
start your own company with AI, no
employees, solve a problem, keep
interviewing, and you'll go to the head
of the class, meaning you'll be
recruited first. Um, Michig uh sentiment
terrible and the conference board joined
this. It had held up much better than
expected. So, sentiment is terrible. I
think diesel prices 650 and gasoline
still a problem. Average hourly earnings
a problem surprisingly up only 0.1 uh
maybe because of mix shift a lot of
technology jobs uh uh tailing off those
are high paid jobs so uh this is coming
under pressure 3% and we think uh
productivity as I showed you on that
other chart is going to go well above 3%
so we do think we do think there's going
to be a labor shortage and that
compensation per manh hour average
hourly earnings growth rate will uh turn
around as the economic momentum becomes
clearer. Um personal saving rate again
down very low by historical standards uh
and that's because affordability
probably people digging into their
savings on the high end consumer with
the with uh equities near an all-time
high maybe uh there's a little bit of a
decline in their saving rate as well. We
we haven't seen that data yet. Uh
existing home sales still in a
recession, just terrible. And uh one of
the reasons, of course, is uh mortgage
rates have turned up. They're above 7%.
Uh so this is a big problem. And uh to
move houses well, and this is the new
one family houses for sale, inventory
inventory is near all-time highs. These
builders are cutting prices to move uh
that inventory, but it's still at a high
level. Interestingly, there was a little
bit of a tick up. This is a three-month
moving average basis for existing home
price inflation. We thought that those
prices would start falling as well if
people really wanted to move their
houses as uh rates go up. Still think
that could be the case. Here are the
rates moving back up. Um not
surprisingly
uh here's manufacturing it is moved out
of recession. So that rolling recession
that we saw there it is out uh and one
of the reasons is capital spending
non-defense capital goods ex uh aircraft
uh and as we know defense spending you
can add to this the this is booming but
I like to remind people that it was kind
of capped uh from the tech and telecom
bubble and bust on it just stopped.
Again, looking at uh if we were looking
at this as a a stock, we'd say the
longer the base, the the larger the
breakout, and that certainly is
happening. And the more sustained, I
would say, too. Uh trade balance. Uh we
think this is going to continue
deteriorating. In this last month, we
saw uh our imports up, I believe, 2.8,
our exports down 2.2. too. Uh so we are
growing faster than the rest of the
world. That's why this will continue to
uh deteriorate. President Trump may not
like that, but um it's the flip side of
it of a trade deficit is a capital
surplus. We're getting a lot more
foreign investment and foreign direct
investment in bricks and mortar um uh
than I think many people expected.
Here's domestic profitability.
Productivity going up will probably
continue to help it. We could go to an
all-time high. Uh you can see where that
was. Uh I think I can't read the date,
but it was a long time ago. Um here you
can see we're going into the uh market
uh indicators. This is quite interesting
to us. So, you can see uh that the
10-year Treasury yield is is has moved
up. Uh and I've given you reasons why.
What's very unusual is that that bottom
indicator metals to gold has not gone up
more than it has. Gold has been falling,
so that would put upward pressure on it.
Uh but metals relative to gold just
hasn't turned. And I'll tell you, we're
seeing so many indicators out of China
that are just terrible. I think I might
have mentioned uh last time around uh
auto auto production in China is
somewhere still in the 30 to 35 million
uh units per year. Uh but their
consumption of autos has dropped from
roughly 30 down to I think 19. change
and interestingly our own auto sales uh
dropped below 16 million uh in in the
latest reading which would have been yes
September and I do believe we're seeing
the impact of Uber Lift affordability on
auto sales uh and so uh I think I think
auto sales have peaked secularly just
like we think uh oil prices have peaked
secularly.
Um and here quickly uh S&P to to oil
still still near a high even though oil
had gone out to 90 to 100. If we're
right on what's going to happen to oil
prices, uh the S&P is going to go up
dramatically relative to oil. And here's
the S&P relative to gold. Again, the
reason we feature this is it was a very
good indicator in the 60s7s
uh uh of the the stock market being in a
world of hurt. Um it started down back
then and we went through a a terrible
bare market from 1966 effectively uh
until 198 um 1982
is when we got back to that 1966 high if
you can believe it or not. Um, so we
were looking at this indicator fading,
fading, and a lot of people focused on
government deficits, government debt.
Isn't this terrible? And we're going
back into the 70s kind of environment.
We are not. We are not uh and happy to
see it tick up again. We think this will
tick up uh to all-time highs uh as the
S&P continues to move up uh with
earnings growth uh and gold perhaps
moves down. Uh and here very nice very
nice turn. Bitcoin to gold uh Bitcoin
going up, gold going down. We've talked
about the correlation between Bitcoin
and gold. Ironically, Bitcoin's known as
digital gold for its store of value
characteristics. Uh, but the correlation
one to the other over over the the study
we did was back to 2019 when
institutions were becoming more
interested. The correlation between the
two is 0.1. No correlation. Recently,
it's been a negative correlation. Uh so
we do think the turn is in here for for
Bitcoin
and uh final market statistics uh you
know if you look at uh credit default
swap so um insurance policies against uh
against bankruptcy and this is bank
credit default swaps. They're very low.
there's no systemic risk even though
private credit is still uh in uh a
difficult moment, shall we say? It's not
feeding back into the banking system.
You can see here this is these are junk
bonds effectively high yield bonds uh
relative to the 10-year Treasury. Again,
a little bit of an uptick here, but you
know, in the context of history, very
low. So, not a worry in the world.
though you can see before uh before uh
recessions they they typically are low.
We don't think we're in a recession at
all. We think we came through a rolling
recession. Um but so far so good. Uh
last chart uh two two last charts here.
So this is AI equities in the purple and
uh this is Kshi's
I think this is Kshi's um bet on will
the Republicans uh uh lose control uh or
not and uh this would say the higher the
black line is the higher the probability
Republicans will stay in control. Um, as
you can see, the probability has dropped
and many people were making the case
that as that happened,
um, that a a Democratic
or a Democratcontrolled
House and Senate would be very bad for
AI. And so they were trying to figure
out a correlation here. As you can see,
these have broken apart. And I think the
reason is if the Senate, if the
Republicans lost the Senate and uh and
the House, uh all that would mean would
be gridlock because we have the same
president who basically um uh
threw out uh President Biden's executive
order on AI, which could have become
very punishing, and put in and we know
this has been the topic of of the week.
Uh, are we going to regulate AI giving
the hugging given the hugging face uh
incident, the hacks we've heard about
recently? And this administration has
come down squarely on you self-regulate
and oh by the way you uh large language
model companies uh are liable if
something goes really wrong here. So uh
that was interesting. Uh and there is
this worry in terms of the credit
default uh swabs, this worry about
hyperscalers. And it is interesting,
look at the green there, uh to see that
those in the context of a short history.
Uh you know, they they were cash
fortresses for for years and they didn't
need to tap the debt markets at all. Um
and yet uh here they are tapping the
debt markets and this is quite an
unusual moment. So you know their uh
credit default swaps uh are
deteriorating. Going up means they're
deteriorating. Uh and and uh we're
seeing the the investment grade tick up
that's in black. Uh the high yield the
junk bond in purple those are ticking up
more. Um, and I'm sure the Neocloud
providers are a big part of the reason
for that. Um, as is I I don't know if
Oracle was downgraded or I don't know if
it was downgraded. It may be featuring
in there as well. Uh, so with that,
there's a a quick trip through lots of
data. Uh, so thank you for joining us
and uh I hope you have a lovely weekend.